Chapter 33.
In her furred travelling-dress, Estella seemed more delicately beautiful than she
had ever seemed yet, even in my eyes. Her manner was more winning than she had cared
to let it be to me before, and I thought I saw Miss Havisham’s influence in the change.
We stood in the Inn Yard while she pointed out her luggage to me,
and when it was all collected I remembered—having forgotten everything
but herself in the meanwhile—that I knew nothing of her destination.
“I am going to Richmond,” she told me. “Our lesson is, that there are two Richmonds,
one in Surrey and one in Yorkshire, and that mine is the Surrey Richmond. The distance is
ten miles. I am to have a carriage, and you are to take me. This is my purse,
and you are to pay my charges out of it. O, you must take the purse! We have no choice,
you and I, but to obey our instructions. We are not free to follow our own devices, you and I.”
As she looked at me in giving me the purse, I hoped there was an
inner meaning in her words. She said them slightingly, but not with displeasure.
“A carriage will have to be sent for, Estella. Will you rest here a little?”
“Yes, I am to rest here a little,
and I am to drink some tea, and you are to take care of me the while.”
She drew her arm through mine, as if it must be done, and I requested a waiter
who had been staring at the coach like a man who had never seen such a thing in his life,
to show us a private sitting-room. Upon that, he pulled out a napkin,
as if it were a magic clue without which he couldn’t find the way upstairs, and led us to the
black hole of the establishment, fitted up with a diminishing mirror (quite a superfluous article,
considering the hole’s proportions), an anchovy sauce-cruet, and somebody’s pattens.
On my objecting to this retreat, he took us into another room with a dinner-table for thirty,
and in the grate a scorched leaf of a copy-book under a bushel of coal-dust. Having looked at
this extinct conflagration and shaken his head, he took my order; which, proving to be merely,
“Some tea for the lady,” sent him out of the room in a very low state of mind.
I was, and I am, sensible that the air of this chamber, in its strong combination of stable with
soup-stock, might have led one to infer that the coaching department was not doing well,
and that the enterprising proprietor was boiling down the horses for the refreshment department.
Yet the room was all in all to me, Estella being in it. I thought that with her I could have been
happy there for life. (I was not at all happy there at the time, observe, and I knew it well.)
“Where are you going to, at Richmond?” I asked Estella.
“I am going to live,” said she, “at a great expense, with a lady there,
who has the power—or says she has—of taking me about, and introducing me,
and showing people to me and showing me to people.”
“I suppose you will be glad of variety and admiration?”
“Yes, I suppose so.”
She answered so carelessly, that I said, “You speak of yourself as if you were some one else.”
“Where did you learn how I speak of others?
Come, come,” said Estella, smiling delightfully, “you must not expect me to go to school to you;
I must talk in my own way. How do you thrive with Mr. Pocket?”
“I live quite pleasantly there; at least—” It appeared to me that I was losing a chance.
“At least?” repeated Estella.
“As pleasantly as I could anywhere, away from you.”
“You silly boy,” said Estella, quite composedly, “how can you talk such
nonsense? Your friend Mr. Matthew, I believe, is superior to the rest of his family?”
“Very superior indeed. He is nobody’s enemy—”
“Don’t add but his own,” interposed Estella, “for I hate that class of man. But he really
is disinterested, and above small jealousy and spite, I have heard?”
“I am sure I have every reason to say so.”
“You have not every reason to say so of the rest of his people,” said Estella,
nodding at me with an expression of face that was at once grave and rallying, “for they beset Miss
Havisham with reports and insinuations to your disadvantage. They watch you, misrepresent you,
write letters about you (anonymous sometimes), and you are the torment and the occupation
of their lives. You can scarcely realise to yourself the hatred those people feel for you.”
“They do me no harm, I hope?”
Instead of answering, Estella burst out laughing. This was very singular to me,
and I looked at her in considerable perplexity. When she left off—and she had not laughed
languidly, but with real enjoyment—I said, in my diffident way with her,—
“I hope I may suppose that you would not be amused if they did me any harm.”
“No, no you may be sure of that,” said Estella. “You may be certain that I laugh because they
fail. O, those people with Miss Havisham, and the tortures they undergo!” She laughed again,
and even now when she had told me why, her laughter was very singular to me, for I could
not doubt its being genuine, and yet it seemed too much for the occasion. I thought there must
really be something more here than I knew; she saw the thought in my mind, and answered it.
“It is not easy for even you.” said Estella, “to know what satisfaction it gives me to see those
people thwarted, or what an enjoyable sense of the ridiculous I have when they are made ridiculous.
For you were not brought up in that strange house from a mere baby. I was. You had not your
little wits sharpened by their intriguing against you, suppressed and defenceless,
under the mask of sympathy and pity and what not that is soft and soothing. I had. You did not
gradually open your round childish eyes wider and wider to the discovery of that impostor
of a woman who calculates her stores of peace of mind for when she wakes up in the night. I did.”
It was no laughing matter with Estella now,
nor was she summoning these remembrances from any shallow place. I would not have
been the cause of that look of hers for all my expectations in a heap.
“Two things I can tell you,” said Estella. “First, notwithstanding the proverb that constant
dropping will wear away a stone, you may set your mind at rest that these
people never will—never would in a hundred years—impair your ground with Miss Havisham,
in any particular, great or small. Second, I am beholden to you as the
cause of their being so busy and so mean in vain, and there is my hand upon it.”
As she gave it to me playfully,—for her darker mood had been but momentary—I held it and put
it to my lips. “You ridiculous boy,” said Estella, “will you never take warning? Or
do you kiss my hand in the same spirit in which I once let you kiss my cheek?”
“What spirit was that?” said I.
“I must think a moment. A spirit of contempt for the fawners and plotters.”
“If I say yes, may I kiss the cheek again?”
“You should have asked before you touched the hand. But, yes, if you like.”
I leaned down, and her calm face was like a statue’s.
“Now,” said Estella, gliding away the instant I touched her cheek,
“you are to take care that I have some tea, and you are to take me to Richmond.”
Her reverting to this tone as if our association were forced upon us, and we were mere puppets,
gave me pain; but everything in our intercourse did give me pain. Whatever
her tone with me happened to be, I could put no trust in it, and build no hope on it;
and yet I went on against trust and against hope. Why repeat it a thousand times? So it always was.
I rang for the tea, and the waiter, reappearing with his magic clue, brought in by degrees some
fifty adjuncts to that refreshment, but of tea not a glimpse. A teaboard, cups and saucers, plates,
knives and forks (including carvers), spoons (various), salt-cellars, a meek little muffin
confined with the utmost precaution under a strong iron cover, Moses in the bulrushes typified by a
soft bit of butter in a quantity of parsley, a pale loaf with a powdered head, two proof
impressions of the bars of the kitchen fireplace on triangular bits of bread, and ultimately a
fat family urn; which the waiter staggered in with, expressing in his countenance burden and
suffering. After a prolonged absence at this stage of the entertainment, he at length came back with
a casket of precious appearance containing twigs. These I steeped in hot water, and so
from the whole of these appliances extracted one cup of I don’t know what for Estella.
The bill paid, and the waiter remembered, and the ostler not forgotten, and the chambermaid taken
into consideration,—in a word, the whole house bribed into a state of contempt and animosity,
and Estella’s purse much lightened,—we got into our post-coach and drove away. Turning into
Cheapside and rattling up Newgate Street, we were soon under the walls of which I was so ashamed.
“What place is that?” Estella asked me.
I made a foolish pretence of not at first recognising it,
and then told her. As she looked at it, and drew in her head again, murmuring,
“Wretches!” I would not have confessed to my visit for any consideration.
“Mr. Jaggers,” said I, by way of putting it neatly on somebody else,
“has the reputation of being more in the secrets of that dismal place than any man in London.”
“He is more in the secrets of every place, I think,” said Estella, in a low voice.
“You have been accustomed to see him often, I suppose?”
“I have been accustomed to see him at uncertain intervals,
ever since I can remember. But I know him no better now, than I did before I could speak
plainly. What is your own experience of him? Do you advance with him?”
“Once habituated to his distrustful manner,” said I, “I have done very well.”
“Are you intimate?” “I have dined with him at his private house.”
“I fancy,” said Estella, shrinking “that must be a curious place.”
“It is a curious place.”
I should have been chary of discussing my guardian too freely even with her;
but I should have gone on with the subject so far as to describe the dinner in Gerrard Street,
if we had not then come into a sudden glare of gas. It seemed, while it lasted,
to be all alight and alive with that inexplicable feeling I had had before;
and when we were out of it, I was as much dazed for a few moments as if I had been in lightning.
So we fell into other talk, and it was principally about the way by
which we were travelling, and about what parts of London lay on this side of it,
and what on that. The great city was almost new to her, she told me,
for she had never left Miss Havisham’s neighbourhood until she had gone to France, and
she had merely passed through London then in going and returning. I asked her if my guardian had any
charge of her while she remained here? To that she emphatically said “God forbid!” and no more.
It was impossible for me to avoid seeing that she cared to attract me;
that she made herself winning, and would have won me even if the task had needed pains. Yet
this made me none the happier, for even if she had not taken that tone of our being disposed
of by others, I should have felt that she held my heart in her hand because she wilfully chose
to do it, and not because it would have wrung any tenderness in her to crush it and throw it away.
When we passed through Hammersmith, I showed her where Mr. Matthew Pocket lived,
and said it was no great way from Richmond, and that I hoped I should see her sometimes.
“O yes, you are to see me; you are to come when you think proper;
you are to be mentioned to the family; indeed you are already mentioned.”
I inquired was it a large household she was going to be a member of?
“No; there are only two; mother and daughter. The mother is a lady of some station,
though not averse to increasing her income.”
“I wonder Miss Havisham could part with you again so soon.”
“It is a part of Miss Havisham’s plans for me, Pip,” said Estella,
with a sigh, as if she were tired; “I am to write to her constantly and see her
regularly and report how I go on,—I and the jewels,—for they are nearly all mine now.”
It was the first time she had ever called me by my name. Of course she did so purposely,
and knew that I should treasure it up.
We came to Richmond all too soon, and our destination there was a house by the green,—a
staid old house, where hoops and powder and patches, embroidered coats, rolled stockings,
ruffles and swords, had had their court days many a time. Some ancient trees before the
house were still cut into fashions as formal and unnatural as the hoops and wigs and stiff skirts;
but their own allotted places in the great procession of the dead were not far off,
and they would soon drop into them and go the silent way of the rest.
A bell with an old voice—which I dare say in its time had often said to the house,
Here is the green farthingale, Here is the diamond-hilted sword,
Here are the shoes with red heels and the blue solitaire—sounded gravely in the moonlight,
and two cherry-coloured maids came fluttering out to receive Estella. The
doorway soon absorbed her boxes, and she gave me her hand and a smile, and said good-night,
and was absorbed likewise. And still I stood looking at the house, thinking how happy I should
be if I lived there with her, and knowing that I never was happy with her, but always miserable.
I got into the carriage to be taken back to Hammersmith,
and I got in with a bad heart-ache, and I got out with a worse heart-ache. At our own door,
I found little Jane Pocket coming home from a little party escorted by her little lover;
and I envied her little lover, in spite of his being subject to Flopson.
Mr. Pocket was out lecturing; for, he was a most delightful lecturer on domestic economy,
and his treatises on the management of children and servants were considered the very best
text-books on those themes. But Mrs. Pocket was at home, and was in a little difficulty,
on account of the baby’s having been accommodated with a needle-case to keep
him quiet during the unaccountable absence (with a relative in the Foot Guards) of
Millers. And more needles were missing than it could be regarded as quite wholesome for
a patient of such tender years either to apply externally or to take as a tonic.
Mr. Pocket being justly celebrated for giving most excellent practical advice,
and for having a clear and sound perception of things and a highly judicious mind, I had some
notion in my heart-ache of begging him to accept my confidence. But happening to look up at Mrs.
Pocket as she sat reading her book of dignities after prescribing Bed as a sovereign remedy for
baby, I thought—Well—No, I wouldn’t. Chapter 34.